<?xml version="1.0" standalone="yes"?>
<!DOCTYPE library PUBLIC "-//Boost//DTD BoostBook XML V1.0//EN"
     "http://www.boost.org/tools/boostbook/dtd/boostbook.dtd"
[
    <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "program_options.ent" >
    %entities;
]>
<section id="program_options.howto">

  <title>How To</title>

  <para>This section describes how the library can be used in specific
  situations.</para>

<!--

validators
positional options
options groups/hidden options

-->
  <section>
    <title>Non-conventional Syntax</title>
    
    <para>Sometimes, standard command line syntaxes are not enough. For
    example, the gcc compiler has "-frtti" and -fno-rtti" options, and this
    syntax is not directly supported.
    </para>

    <indexterm><primary>additional parser</primary></indexterm>
    <para>For such cases, the library allows the user to provide an
    <firstterm>additional parser</firstterm> -- a function which will be called on each
    command line element, before any processing by the library. If the
    additional parser recognises the syntax, it returns the option name and
    value, which are used directly. The above example can be handled by the
    following code:
    </para>

    <para>
      <programlisting>
pair&lt;string, string&gt; reg_foo(const string&amp; s)
{
    if (s.find("-f") == 0) {
        if (s.substr(2, 3) == "no-")
            return make_pair(s.substr(5), string("false"));
        else
            return make_pair(s.substr(2), string("true"));
    } else {
        return make_pair(string(), string());
    }
}
</programlisting>
      Here's the definition of the additional parser. When parsing the command
      line, we pass the additional parser:
<programlisting>
store(command_line_parser(ac, av).options(desc).extra_parser(reg_foo)
        .run(), vm);
</programlisting>
      The complete example can be found in the "example/custom_syntax.cpp"
      file.                
    </para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Response Files</title>

    <indexterm><primary>response files</primary></indexterm> 

    <para>Some operating system have very low limits of the command line
      length. The common way to work around those limitations is using
      <firstterm>response files</firstterm>.  A response file is just a
      configuration file which uses the same syntax as the command line. If
      the command line specifies a name of response file to use, it's loaded
      and parsed in addition to the command line.  The library does not
      provide direct support for response files, so you'll need to write some
      extra code.
    </para>

    <para>
      First, you need to define an option for the response file:
<programlisting>
("response-file", value&lt;string&gt;(), 
     "can be specified with '@name', too")
</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>Second, you'll need an additional parser to support the standard syntax
    for specifying response files: "@file":
<programlisting><![CDATA[
pair<string, string> at_option_parser(string const&s)
{
    if ('@' == s[0])
        return std::make_pair(string("response-file"), s.substr(1));
    else
        return pair<string, string>();
}
]]>
</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>Finally, when the "response-file" option is found, you'll have to
    load that file and pass it to the command line parser. This part is the
    hardest. We'll use the Boost.Tokenizer library, which works but has some
    limitations. You might also consider Boost.StringAlgo. The code is:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
if (vm.count("response-file")) {
     // Load the file and tokenize it
     ifstream ifs(vm["response-file"].as<string>().c_str());
     if (!ifs) {
         cout << "Could not open the response file\n";
         return 1;
     }
     // Read the whole file into a string
     stringstream ss;
     ss << ifs.rdbuf();
     // Split the file content
     char_separator<char> sep(" \n\r");
     std::string ResponsefileContents( ss.str() );
     tokenizer<char_separator<char> > tok(ResponsefileContents, sep);
     vector<string> args;
     copy(tok.begin(), tok.end(), back_inserter(args));
     // Parse the file and store the options
     store(command_line_parser(args).options(desc).run(), vm);     
}
]]>
</programlisting>
      The complete example can be found in the "example/response_file.cpp"
      file.                
    </para>
 
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Winmain Command Line</title>

    <para>On the Windows operating system, GUI applications receive the
    command line as a single string, not split into elements. For that reason,
    the command line parser cannot be used directly. At least on some
    compilers, it is possible to obtain
    the split command line, but it's not clear if all compilers support the
    same mechanism on all versions of the operating system. The
    <code>split_winmain</code> function is a portable mechanism provided
    by the library.</para>

    <para>Here's an example of use:
<programlisting>
vector&lt;string&gt; args = split_winmain(lpCmdLine);
store(command_line_parser(args).options(desc).run(), vm);
</programlisting>      
      The <code>split_winmain</code> function is overloaded for <code>wchar_t</code> strings, so can
      also be used in Unicode applications.
    </para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Option Groups and Hidden Options</title>

    <para>Having a single instance of the &options_description; class with all
    the program's options can be problematic:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Some options make sense only for specific source, for example,
          configuration files.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The user would prefer some structure in the generated help message.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Some options shouldn't appear in the generated help message at all.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>To solve the above issues, the library allows a programmer to create several
      instances of the &options_description; class, which can be merged in
      different combinations. The following example will define three groups of
      options: command line specific, and two options group for specific program
      modules, only one of which is shown in the generated help message.
    </para>

    <para>Each group is defined using standard syntax. However, you should
      use reasonable names for each &options_description; instance:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
options_description general("General options");
general.add_options()
    ("help", "produce a help message")
    ("help-module", value<string>(),
        "produce a help for a given module")
    ("version", "output the version number")
    ;

options_description gui("GUI options");
gui.add_options()
    ("display", value<string>(), "display to use")
    ;

options_description backend("Backend options");
backend.add_options()
    ("num-threads", value<int>(), "the initial number of threads")
    ;
]]></programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>After declaring options groups, we merge them in two
      combinations. The first will include all options and be used for parsing. The
      second will be used for the "--help" option.
<programlisting>
// Declare an options description instance which will include
// all the options
options_description all("Allowed options");
all.add(general).add(gui).add(backend);

// Declare an options description instance which will be shown
// to the user
options_description visible("Allowed options");
visible.add(general).add(gui);
</programlisting>
    </para>

    <para>What is left is to parse and handle the options:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
variables_map vm;
store(parse_command_line(ac, av, all), vm);

if (vm.count("help")) 
{
    cout << visible;
    return 0;
}
if (vm.count("help-module")) {
    const string& s = vm["help-module"].as<string>();
    if (s == "gui") {
        cout << gui;
    } else if (s == "backend") {
        cout << backend;
    } else {
        cout << "Unknown module '" 
             << s << "' in the --help-module option\n";
        return 1;
    }
    return 0;
}
if (vm.count("num-threads")) {
    cout << "The 'num-threads' options was set to "
         << vm["num-threads"].as<int>() << "\n";            
}                           
]]></programlisting>
      When parsing the command line, all options are allowed. The "--help"
      message, however, does not include the "Backend options" group -- the
      options in that group are hidden. The user can explicitly force the
      display of that options group by passing "--help-module backend"
      option. The complete example can be found in the
      "example/option_groups.cpp" file.
    </para>
  
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Custom Validators</title>

    <para>By default, the conversion of option's value from string into C++
      type is done using iostreams, which sometimes is not convenient. The
      library allows the user to customize the conversion for specific
      classes. In order to do so, the user should provide suitable overload of
      the <code>validate</code> function.
    </para>

    <para>
      Let's first define a simple class:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
struct magic_number {
public:
    magic_number(int n) : n(n) {}
    int n;
};
]]></programlisting> and then overload the <code>validate</code> function:
<programlisting><![CDATA[
void validate(boost::any& v, 
              const std::vector<std::string>& values,
              magic_number* target_type, int)
{
    static regex r("\\d\\d\\d-(\\d\\d\\d)");

    using namespace boost::program_options;

    // Make sure no previous assignment to 'a' was made.
    validators::check_first_occurrence(v);
    // Extract the first string from 'values'. If there is more than
    // one string, it's an error, and exception will be thrown.
    const string& s = validators::get_single_string(values);

    // Do regex match and convert the interesting part to 
    // int.
    smatch match;
    if (regex_match(s, match, r)) {
        v = any(magic_number(lexical_cast<int>(match[1])));
    } else {
        throw validation_error(validation_error::invalid_option_value);
    }        
}
]]>        
</programlisting>The function takes four parameters. The first is the storage
      for the value, and in this case is either empty or contains an instance of
      the <code>magic_number</code> class. The second is the list of strings
      found in the next occurrence of the option. The remaining two parameters
      are needed to workaround the lack of partial template specialization and
      partial function template ordering on some compilers.
    </para>

    <para>The function first checks that we don't try to assign to the same
      option twice. Then it checks that only a single string was passed
      in. Next the string is verified with the help of the Boost.Regex
      library. If that test is passed, the parsed value is stored into the
      <code>v</code> variable.
    </para>

    <para>The complete example can be found in the "example/regex.cpp" file.
    </para>


  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Unicode Support</title>

    <para>To use the library with Unicode, you'd need to:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Use Unicode-aware parsers for Unicode input</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Require Unicode support for options which need it</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>

    <para>Most of the parsers have Unicode versions. For example, the
      &parse_command_line; function has an overload which takes
      <code>wchar_t</code> strings, instead of ordinary <code>char</code>.
    </para>

    <para>Even if some of the parsers are Unicode-aware, it does not mean you
    need to change definition of all the options. In fact, for many options,
    like integer ones, it makes no sense. To make use of Unicode you'll need
    <emphasis>some</emphasis> Unicode-aware options. They are different from
    ordinary options in that they accept <code>wstring</code> input, and
    process it using wide character streams. Creating an Unicode-aware option
    is easy: just use the the <code>wvalue</code> function instead of the
    regular <code>value</code>.
    </para>

    <para>When an ascii parser passes data to an ascii option, or a Unicode
      parser passes data to a Unicode option, the data are not changed at
      all. So, the ascii option will see a string in local 8-bit encoding, and
      the Unicode option will see whatever string was passed as the Unicode
      input.
    </para>

    <para>What happens when Unicode data is passed to an ascii option, and
      vice versa? The library automatically performs the conversion from
      Unicode to local 8-bit encoding. For example, if command line is in
      ascii, but you use <code>wstring</code> options, then the ascii input
      will be converted into Unicode.
    </para>

    <para>To perform the conversion, the library uses the <code>codecvt&lt;wchar_t,
    char&gt;</code> locale facet from the global locale. If
    you want to work with strings that use local 8-bit encoding (as opposed to
    7-bit ascii subset), your application should start with:
      <programlisting>
locale::global(locale(""));
      </programlisting>
      which would set up the conversion facet according to the user's selected
      locale. 
    </para>

    <para>It's wise to check the status of the C++ locale support on your
      implementation, though. The quick test involves three steps:
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Go the the "test" directory and build the "test_convert" binary.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Set some non-ascii locale in the environmemt. On Linux, one can
          run, for example: <screen>
$ export LC_CTYPE=ru_RU.KOI8-R
</screen>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the "test_convert" binary with any non-ascii string in the
            selected encoding as its parameter. If you see a list of Unicode codepoints,
            everything's OK. Otherwise, locale support on your system might be
            broken.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Allowing Unknown Options</title>

      <para>Usually, the library throws an exception on unknown option names. This 
      behaviour can be changed. For example, only some part of your application uses 
      <libraryname>Program_options</libraryname>, and you wish to pass unrecognized options to another part of
      the program, or even to another application.</para>

      <para>To allow unregistered options on the command line, you need to use 
      the &basic_command_line_parser; class for parsing (not &parse_command_line;)
      and call the <methodname alt="boost::program_options::basic_command_line_parser::allow_unregistered">allow_unregistered</methodname> 
      method of that class:
      <programlisting>
parsed_options parsed = 
    command_line_parser(argc, argv).options(desc).allow_unregistered().run();      
      </programlisting>
      
      For each token that looks like an option, but does not have a known name, 
      an instance of &basic_option; will be added to the result. 
      The <code>string_key</code> and <code>value</code> fields of the instance will contain results 
      of syntactic parsing of the token, the <code>unregistered</code> field will be set to <code>true</code>,
      and the <code>original_tokens</code> field will contain the token as it appeared on the command line.
      </para>

      <para>If you want to pass the unrecognized options further, the 
      <functionname alt="boost::program_options::collect_unrecognized">collect_unrecognized</functionname> function can be used.
      The function will collect original tokens for all unrecognized values, and optionally, all found positional options.
      Say, if your code handles a few options, but does not handles positional options at all, you can use the function like this:
      <programlisting>
vector&lt;string&gt; to_pass_further = collect_unrecognized(parsed.options, include_positional);
      </programlisting>
      
      </para>     
            
    </section>

</section>

<!--
     Local Variables:
     mode: nxml
     sgml-indent-data: t
     sgml-parent-document: ("userman.xml" "chapter")
     sgml-set-face: t
     End:
-->
